A Guide to the
Archives and Special Collections Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University
Archives and Special Collections Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University
Sen. Benjamin J. Lambert III Papers 1991-2000
Archives and Special Collections Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University
MS-0009
5.5 linear feet
Sen. Benjamin Lambert III
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated to the department by Sen. Lambert.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born in Henrico County on January 29, 1937, Benjamin Lambert III has been a Virginia state legislator since 1978. He graduated from Virginia Randolph High School in 1955 and Virginia Union University in 1959 with a BA in math. According to the 1959 VUU yearbook, Lambert was class president and a member of the yearbook staff, Who's Who Among Students in American Universities and Colleges, the Math Club, band, the Panhellenic Council and Omega PSI PHI fraternity.
Lambert is an optometrist by profession, having graduated from the Massachusetts College of Optometry and attended the Pennsylvania College of Optometry. He belongs to the Virginia Optometric Association, the American Optometric Association, the National Optometric Association and the Richmond Medical Society.
He is married to Carolyn Morris Lambert and they have four children. Lambert is a member of the Westwood Baptist Church.
Lambert was a member of the Virginia House of Delegates from 1978-1985. He has been a senator representing the 9th district since 1986. During his senator career, he has served on numerous committees, including chairing the Subcommittee on Higher Education.
Throughout his career, Lambert has led a very active civic life with service to a number of organizations such as the NAACP, the Richmond Crusade for Voters, the Jackson Ward Civic Association, the Richmond Jaycees and the North Richmond YMCA. As of the year 2000, Lambert was serving on the boards of Consolidated Bank and Trust, Dominion Resources Inc., USA Education Inc., Virginia Union University, VCU Health Systems Authority, Virginia College Fund, Virginia Randolph Foundation, the Black History Museum and the Barksdale Theatre.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists primarily of Sen. Lambert's Correspondence from constituents and lobby groups during the years 1991-2000. Included with much of the correspondence are fact sheets and reports compiled specifically for consideration by the legislators during the legislative sessions. It provides a window on the issues of the times. In some cases, this correspondence portrays the tragic stories of those "less fortunate" as they provide hearbreaking detail of tragedy and misfortune which the writers hope the passage or voting down of a new piece of legislation will correct.
There is a smaller segment of correspondence from Lambert to his constituents. The collection will continue to grow as Lambert transfers these materials each year to VUU Special Collections from his senate offices.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by series and chronological therein.
Organization
Series 1. Correspondence
Series 2. Legislative Reports
Series 3. Constituent Ballots
Series 4. Fact Sheets
Series 5. Miscellaneous Certificates, Awards, Etc
Series 6. Schedules
Contents List
- Series 1. Correspondence 1991-2000
  The correspondence files contain primarily letters from constituents and lobbyists to Sen. Lambert seeking his support for certain legislation or asking him to vote down legislation that would harm their interests.
  - Correspondence 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1997 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, January-Feb. 1998 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Feb.-Dec. 1998 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, January 1999 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, Feb. 1-21 1999 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, Jan-Feb. 2000 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, Feb.-April 2000 (Box 8)
- Series 2. Legislative Reports 1996-2000
  These are reports and agendas published by various special interest groups, lobbies and public agencies specifically for the legislators' consideration during a particular session.
  - Legislative Reports 1996-1997 (Box 9)
  - Legislative Reports 1996-1997 (Box 10)
  - Legislative Reports 1997-1999 (Box 11)
  - Legislative Reports 1998-1999 (Box 12)
  - Legislative Reports 1999-2000 (Box 13)
- Series 3. Constituent Ballots 1996-2000
  These ballots were submitted on a standardized form with the constituent's name and address, the issue, their position favoring or opposing, and any message.
  - Constituent Ballots 1996-2000 (Box 14)
- Series 4. Fact Sheets 1996-2000
  These are simple, usually one-page documents summarizing the position of a particular group, agency or lobby in regards to an issue before the Legislature.
  - Fact Sheets 1996-2000 (Box 14)
- Series 5. Miscellaneous 1993-2000
  - Papa John's Gift Certificate (Box 14)
  - Admission Ticket to Governor's Address January 14, 1998 (Box 14)
  - Junior Achievement Certificate of Appreciation (Box 14)
  - General Assembly Classic Basketball Flier 2000 (Box 14)
  - Architect's Rendering of Maggie Walker High School Renovation (Box 14)
  - Announcement for Surprise Reception for Jane Kusiak (Box 14)
  - Virginia Nurses Association Certificate of Appreciation (Box 14)
  - Lambert's Floor Address Concerning the Governor's Amendments to Senate Bill 584 (Box 14)
  - Virginia Council Against Poverty Certificate of Participation in Walk-A-Mile Project (Box 14)
  - Black History Month Certificate of Recognition (Box 14)
  - Tobacco Company Restaurant Executive Dining Member Invitation (Box 14)
  - News Release Concerning Grants for MCV and Richmond Community Action Program (Box 14)
  - Resolutions Noting with Sadness the Passing of Dr. Barrington Bowser, Nina Adady, Jackson Rozier, Jr., Dr. Bonita Settle, Mary Melton Jones and Carroll Saine (Box 14)
  - Courts of Justice Committee Meeting Notifications (Box 14)
- Series 5. Schedules 1998-2000
  These are small formatted sheets with Sen. Lambert's daily schedules of meetings, receptions, dinners, etc. Some contain handwritten changes or additions.
  - Schedules 1998-2000 (Box 14)